Guide to the North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company Archives, 1850, 1888-2000s and undated, bulk 1920-2008 RL.00936
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Exhibit Materials, 1940s, 1960s-2000s, and undated; 1970s-2000s; 25 boxes
  - Clipping, policy holders' meeting photographs, 1974, circa 1995, box size: 22x30 inches (Box OV1)
  - Exhibit materials: oversize reproductions and captions (in original order as received) (Box OV14-OV22)
  - MEAC exhibit, 1993, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV23)
  - "Stairwell Initiative," circa 1995, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV23)
  - NC Mutual building, circa 1980, box size: 20x24 inches (Box OV24)
  - Exhibit materials, 1943, circa 1963, and undated, box size: 24x36 inches (Box OV44)
  - Exhibit materials, mixed panels and images, 1980s?, box size: 21x25 inches (Box OV50)
  - Exhibit materials, mixed panels and images, 1980s? (Box OV51)
  - Oversize exhibit label panels, 1980s?, Labels measure approximately 36x4 inches.; 6 items (Oversize-folder 2)
  - Bound set of blueprints used for construction of Exhibit Hall room, NC Mutual office, Chapel Hill Street, Durham, N.C., 1960s? (Oversize-folder 4)
  - Assorted exhibit photographs, undated (Box 186)
- Memorabilia and Artifacts, 1923-2008 and undated; 1970s-2000s; 16 boxes
  Contains a wide variety of items that document recognition of achievements, advertising campaigns, and company and employee milestones throughout the history of NCM. Organized into four subseries: Artifacts, Awards and Memorabilia, Plaques, and Promotional Items.
  - Artifacts, 1916-2008 and undated
    Material includes a very early papers portfolio probably belonging to E.R. Merrick; a glass ornament; medical supplies; sales logs; an early 20th century leather satchel with the company name (oversize box); and a large 1950s or 1960s-era travel case housing an insurance sales training kit.
    - "Valuable Papers" portfolio and contents, 1916-1919, 6 folders (Box 90-A)
      Promotional folded portfolio measuring 5.0 x 10.75 inches, stamped on cover with "Valuable Papers, Compliments of North Carolina Mutual and Provident Association," plus a group of documents originally filed within. Probably belonged to E.R. Merrick. Original contents bearing his name include receipts for personal house furnishings, a piano, and baby furniture, among others. For preservation purposes, papers are now housed in separate folders.
    - "Historical St. Joseph's, 1891" - clear glass flat hexagonal ornament (20th century) (Box 90)
    - Artifacts, 3 large boxes (Box 91-93)
    - Life insurance training kit in green faux-leather travel case (with transparencies, manuals, and films) (Box 179)
    - Puzzle of NCM building, undated; 2 folders (Box 188)
  - Awards and Memorabilia, 1953-2003 and undated
    The Awards and Memorabilia Subseries houses publicity for insurance coverage and charitable giving, and awards and certificates for NCM employees, as well as awards received by NCM from external organizations. Includes a company award featuring a bronzed shoe belonging to C.C. Spaulding, and two copies of the Merrick-Moore Award. Also includes a 1943 Western Union telegram from then-governor of N.C. Broughton to C.C. Spaulding concerning the launching ceremony of the U.S.S. Merrick (box 90). The first box is arranged in two groups of folders, beginning with memorabilia (chiefly publicity and programs), and then awards.
    - Printed materials and papers, 11 folders (Box 90)
    - Framed and artifactual items, 2 large boxes (Box 94)
    - Framed and artifactual items (Box 95)
    - Employee certificate, undated (Box 188)
  - Plaques, 1959-2008 and undated; 7 large boxes
    Two groups of awards: plaques marking achievements within the company of its employees and officials, and plaques received by NCM honoring the company for its contributions to the community, commemorating its lifetime membership in the NAACP, and other milestones.
    - Various plaques and awards (Box 96)
    - Various plaques and awards (Box 97)
    - Various plaques and awards (Box 98)
    - Various plaques and awards (Box 99)
    - Various plaques and awards (Box 100)
    - Various plaques and awards (Box 101)
    - Various plaques and awards (Box 102)
  - Promotional Items, circa 1950-2002 and undated
    Consists of both printed material and artifacts, including holiday cards, pocket calendars, fans, match books series with leaders from the civil rights movement, blank baby books, and bookmarks, among many other items.
    - Promotional NCM paper fans, circa 1960s-1998 and undated (Box 90-A)
    - Printed materials, 9 folders (Box 90)
    - Artifactual items, 1 large box (Box 103)
  - Memorabilia and Artifacts Oversize Boxes
    - Certificates, 1962-2005, box size: 11x14 inches (Box OV9)
    - Article About Mutual Plaza Dedication (deframed), 1966, box size: 11x14 inches (Box OV9)
    - Programs, awards, and certificates, 1923-2004, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV23)
    - A.M. Best Certification of Financial Strength Rating, 2006, Feb. 10, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV23)
    - Prudential Insurance plaque, 1967, box size: 20x24 inches (Box OV24)
    - Carrier bag, early 20th c.?, box size: 20x24 inches (Box OV25)
    - Advertising Federation award, 1974, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV26)
    - Certificate from UNC President commemorating NCM's centennial, 1998, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV26)
    - "An Album of the American Family," 1980, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV26)
    - Federal Housing Administration Award, 1959, June 1, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV26)
    - "Official Welcome to Baltimore" certificate, 1998, Sep. 14, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV26)
    - Durham County Board of County Commissioners resolution commemorating NCM's 95th anniversary, 1993, Oct. 11, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV26)
    - Durham resolution honoring NCM 100th anniversary (framed), 1998, box size: 23x31 inches (Box OV45)
    - Plaques, 1991-1997 and undated, box size: 17x21 inches (Box OV46)
    - NCM visitor register, 1924-1955, box size: 12x16 inches (Box OV48)
- Other Organizations, 1927-2008 and undated; 9 boxes
  Contains documents from companies which NCM acquired, and companies with which NCM shared a relationship (or from which it obtained information for planning). These companies include: Wright Mutual Insurance Company, Lincoln National Life Foundation, Inc., the National Insurance Association (NIA), NCM Capital, and Mortgage Company of Durham.
  Box 104 contains fragile material and is slated for preservation photocopying. Please contact Research Services to use this material.
  - Lincoln National Life Foundation, Inc., 1973-1975
    Created to administer the Lincoln National Life Museum, the Foundation provided an avenue for charitable, tax-exempt contributions of Lincoln memorabilia to the museum. It appears that the NCM Corporate Planning department requested information from the Lincoln National Life Foundation regarding its annual report and bylaws in 1975.
    - Lincoln National Life Foundation documents, 1973-1975 (Box 104)
  - Mortgage Company of Durham, 1929-1941
    Founded in 1929 by C.C. Spaulding, E.R. Merrick, and R.L. McDougald to provide greater financial independence for black businesses in Durham, N.C. Although this company stood as a separate corporate entity from NCM, many of the members of the Executive Committee were leaders at NCM, and the company was somewhat connected with NCM in practice. The material consists of the early minutes of the Executive Committee of the Mortgage Company of Durham.
    [Fragile and slated for preservation photocopying. Please contact Research Services to use this material.]
    - Minutes of the Executive Committee of the Mortgage Company of Durham, 1929-1941, 2 folders (Box 104)
  - National Insurance Association, 1927, 1951-1964, 1975-2008, and undated
    Established in 1921 as the National Negro Insurance Association (later renamed National Insurance Association or NIA), and was created in order to promote and represent the mutual interests of insurance companies that were owned and operated by African Americans. C.C. Spaulding was elected as the first president of the association and NCM has remained one of the largest member companies of the organization to the present. NCM employees have regularly served on the Board of Directors and as officers for the NIA.
    - Assorted printed material and miscellaneous documents, 2005-2008 (Box 104)
    - NIA brochure, 2007 and undated (Box 104)
    - Assorted convention planning material, 2006-2007 (Box 105)
    - NIA annual convention programs, 2002-2004, 2006-2008 (Box 105)
    - Oversize poster, NIA annual convention, Las Vegas, 2003, box size: 24x30 inches; 2 duplicate copies (Box OV52)
    - 44th Institute in Agency Management, 2000 (Box 105)
    - Audit report, 1979-1980 (Box 105)
    - By-laws and related items, 1927, 1951-1964, 1991-1999 (Box 105)
    - Committees and other NIA files, 1991-1996 (Box 105)
    - Conferences and other pamphlets, 1988, 1998-2002 (Box 105)
    - Excerpts on notable African Americans, Little Known History of the Negro, undated (Box 105)
    - NIA corporate policies, plans, job descriptions, 1975 and undated (Box 105)
    - NIA tax files, 1985, 1991-1997 (Box 105)
    - NIA tax files and IRS correspondence, 1986-1991, 2 folders (Box 105)
    - Resumes, 1981-1982 and undated (Box 105)
    - Surveys, studies, workshops, and other material, 2000-2001 (Box 105)
    - NIA pamphlets, newsletters, correspondence, and printed material, 1989-1998 and undated (Box 105)
    - NIA Golden Anniversary scrapbook, 1970 (Box 106)
    - Poster of NIA presidents, circa 1970, box size: 22x30 inches (Box OV1)
    - 66th National Insurance Month posters, 2000 May, box size: 20x24 inches (Box OV2)
  - NCM Capital, 1986-1994 and undated
    Maceo Sloan of North Carolina Mutual founded NCM Capital in 1986. NCM is a parent company of NCM Capital. Contents include Board records, reports, and general business files.
    - NCM Capital miscellaneous business files, 1987-1988, 3 folders (Box 106)
    - NCM Capital Board and business files, 1986-1989 and undated, 26 folders (Box 107)
    - NCM Capital reports and correspondence, 1989-1994 and undated, 22 folders (Box 108)
    - NCM Capital correspondence, reports, minutes, and business files, 1986-1990 and undated, 18 folders (Box 109)
  - Wright Mutual Insurance Company, 1942-1967, 1985-2000
    Records of the Wright Mutual Insurance Company, acquired by NC Mutual in 2000.
    - Foreclosure proceedings and legal research, 1985-1993 (Box 109)
    - Legal documents, 1994 (Box 109)
    - Appraisal for home office, 1988 (Box 110)
    - Board of Directors, minutes, 1990-1999 (Box 110)
    - Board of Directors, notices, 1998 (Box 110)
    - Certificates of Authority and Certificates of Interest, 1963, 1967, 1993-1999 (Box 110)
    - Complaints, 1994-1998 (Box 110)
    - Correspondence from Mich. Treasury Dept. and Mich. Dept. of Insurance, 1942-1946 (Box 110)
    - Dreifus Insurance Exchange Agency, 1990-1998 (Box 110)
    - Kaid Almadrahi case, 1990-1992 (Box 110)
    - Miscellaneous Insurance Coverage for Wright Mutual, 1999 (Box 110)
    - Notice to policyholders of NC Mutual merger and late policy payment notices, 1999, 2000 Dec. (Box 110)
    - Omni-Care Health Plan, 1997-1999 (Box 110)
    - Photos of Board of Directors and information booklet, 1987 (Box 110)
    - Lincoln National Pension benefit quote summaries and benefit payouts, 1980-1987 (Box 110)
    - Pension plan, 1987-1999 (Box 110)
    - Amended bylaws, 1967, 1990 (Box 111)
    - Articles of Association, 1942 (Box 111)
    - Certificates of Amendment, 1945, 1959, 1966, 1985 (Box 111)
    - Certificate of Authority, 1942-1944 (Box 111)
    - Cynthia Thomas-Riley case, 1994-1997, 3 folders (Box 111)
    - Deed for home office, 1961 (Box 111)
    - Foreclosure documents and notes, 1975-1993, 2 folders (Box 111)
    - Landlord-tenant decisions, 1991-1994, 2 folders (Box 111)
    - Legal complaints against Wright Mutual, 1991-1993 (Box 111)
    - Mortgage foreclosure proceedings, 1991-1993 (Box 111)
    - Papers regarding incorporation and connection with Pilgrims Mutual Aid Society, 1942-1944 (Box 111)
    - Board of Directors and Executive Committee minutes, 1954-1973, 9 folders (Box 112)
    - General contents of Board of Directors and Executive Committee minutes binders, copyrighted 1945 (Box 112)
    - Wright Mutual Insurance Company brochure, circa 1963 (Box 112)
- Photographic Materials, 1888-2008 and undated; 24 boxes
  The thousands of photographs in this series document the history of North Carolina Mutual Insurance through images of its employees and their families, buildings and other places, and company events. The images range from formal portraits and group shots to snapshots taken at banquets, conventions, meetings, on trips, and around the office.
  There are many 19th century photographs of NCM leaders and their families, staff, including women workers, the earliest home office buildings, office interiors, and community events.
  Individuals depicted in later images include NCM officers, employees, their families, and prominent figures such as Robert F. Kennedy, Martin Luther King, Jr., Spiro Agnew, Jesse Jackson, ambassadors, and other politicians. Many significant original images were reproduced by NCM in various sizes and for various purposes; some of these reappear in the Exhibits Series material.
  The bulk of the 20th century images were produced by the Public Relations Department for The Whetstone and The Pilot and are therefore often marked for cropping and resizing. Although some images are captioned with names, years, and locations, many are unmarked and many dates have been estimated. Some related paper material, such as clippings, biographical sketches, speeches, copies of publications, and memos transmitting the images, can also be found with the prints.
  Materials are arranged into subseries by format. There are also slides, negatives, and negative reproductions found with corresponding photographs in the Prints Subseries.
  Comprising the bulk of the series, the Prints Subseries is arranged into Events, Historic Images, Other Public Relations, People, and Places Subseries. There is considerable overlap, however, for example between Events and People. Many related items are also found in the Exhibit Material Series.
  Large-format photographs and albums are located in the Oversize Prints section listed at the end of this series. These items include historic images of the company's early offices, portraits of senior administrators, group shots at banquets and other events, and images of the NCM home office buildings. Sizes range from 11x14 inches to roughly 32x40 inches, as well as a very large panoramic print of the early home office on Parrish Street, 27x75" (closed to use; digital viewing copy is available).
  - Negatives, 1900-2008 and undated
    Contains negatives and negative reproductions stored separately from prints. Items are arranged in loose chronological order and then into broad categories by content. Negatives directly associated with prints may also be located in the Photographic Prints subseries.
    Original negatives are closed to use; viewing copies may be requested. Please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use these materials.
    - People and places, 1900-1950, 21 negatives (Box 113)
    - People, events, and places, 1940-1968, 11 negatives (Box 113)
    - People, 1960-1980, 13 negatives (Box 113)
    - Events, 1960-1980, 3 negatives (Box 113)
    - People and office, 1980-1990, 2 folders; 25 negatives (Box 113)
    - Events, 1980-1990, 6 folders; 57 negatives (Box 113)
    - People and office, 1990-2000, 2 folders; 20 negatives (Box 114)
    - Events, 1990-2000, 3 folders; 46 negatives (Box 114)
    - People, 2000-2008, 3 folders; 9 negatives (Box 114)
    - Events, undated (Box 186)
  - Photographic Prints, 1888-2008 and undated
    Mostly produced by the Public Relations department for publications such as The Whetstone and The Pilot, the prints are arranged into Events, Historic Images, Other Public Relations, People, and Places subseries, and within, chronologically.
    Of note in this series are historic photographs of North Carolina Mutual offices, leaders, and staff; as well as early images of the families of its founders. These early images were arranged in various groupings by staff, and are found in other series in the collection, especially as reproductions in the Printed Materials Series.
    Formats include 19th century and early 20th century prints such as cartes-de-visite, platinum, and gelatin silver prints, as well as modern black-and-white prints. One may also find negatives, slides and some related paper records in the series. Panoramic prints, largely associated with events, and other large format images are found in the Oversize Prints section listed at the end of the series.
    - Events, 1944-2008 and undated
      Arranged chronologically, these images depict banquets, conventions, trips, and meetings hosted or attended by NCM staff. Most but not all were labeled. Significant events include annual meetings of the National Insurance Association, a 1964 speech by Robert F. Kennedy, a 1964 trip to Mexico and Central America, and the celebration of NCM's 85th anniversary in 1983. Other events include awards ceremonies, retirement celebrations, the Annual Policy Holders' Meeting, Founders' Day, enrollment drives, and charitable events, such as an AIDS Walk and blood drives. Prominent event titles are included. Individuals depicted include NCM officers, employees, their families, politicians, and figures such as Robert F. Kennedy, Spiro Agnew, Jesse Jackson, and the Nigerian ambassador to the U.S. Some negatives and related paper documents are also included.
      - Conferences and meetings, 1944-1970, 2 folders; 114 prints (Box 114)
      - Cloudburst, 1960-1985, 20 prints (Box 114)
      - Unidentified banquet in large ballroom, Chicago photographer stamped on back, black-and-white print, circa 1950s, Photograph has adhered to its glass covering; handle with care. (Box 180)
        May be North Carolina Mutual Chicago office event. Print measures approximately 20x12 inches.
      - School in Agency Management, 1962, 1 print (Box 114)
      - Various events, 1963 and undated, 6 prints (Box 114)
      - Ambassador of Nigeria visit, 1964 Feb. 23, 18 prints (Box 114)
      - Spaulding trip to Mexico and Central America, 1964, 76 prints (Box 114)
      - Spaulding convention, 1967, 11 prints (Box 114)
      - White House event, 1969 May 12, 2 prints (Box 114)
      - NIA Convention in Richmond, 1970, 2 folders; 50 prints (Box 114)
      - John Avery Boys' Club event, circa 1970s, 2 prints (Box 115)
      - Events, 1970-1980, 4 prints (Box 115)
      - NIA Convention in Houston, 1980, 2 folders; 68 prints (Box 115)
      - Tailgate party, 1980 Sept., 20 prints (Box 115)
      - Events, 1980-1990, 3 folders; 263 prints (Box 115)
      - NIA Convention in Atlanta, 1981, 45 prints (Box 115)
      - 85th Anniversary events, 1983, 8 of 18 folders; 175 prints (Box 115)
      - 85th Anniversary events, 1983, 10 of 18 folders; 139 prints (Box 116)
      - Various events, 1980s, 3 prints (Box 116)
      - Dr. Cleland tribute, 1985, 14 prints (Box 116)
      - Russell Blunt reception, 1986, 9 prints (Box 116)
      - Annual policy holder's meeting, 1968, 5 prints (Box 116)
      - Blood drive, circa 1986, 13 prints (Box 116)
      - Olympic Festival, 1987, 18 prints (Box 116)
      - Sales Manager School, 1987, 43 prints (Box 116)
      - Awards luncheon, 1989 May 19, 12 prints (Box 116)
      - Convention and trip snapshots, 1989-1995, 2 folders; 166 prints (Box 116)
      - Field Accounting System training, circa 1990, 48 prints (Box 116)
      - Fellowship event, circa 1990, 37 prints (Box 116)
      - 94th Founders Day, 1992, 60 prints (Box 116)
      - Ron Brown Reception, 1992, 9 prints (Box 116)
      - Annual Policyholders' Meeting, 1993, 1994, 2 folders (Box 116)
      - Proactive Management Workshop, 1994, 1 print (Box 116)
      - Events, 1990-2000, 1 of 18 folders; 52 prints (Box 116)
      - Events, 1990-2000, 2-9 of 18 folders; 942 prints (Box 117)
      - Events, 1990-2000, 10-18 of 18 folders; 748 prints (Box 118)
      - Johnny Cochran reception, 1996, 7 prints (Box 118)
      - Stagville event, 1997, 89 prints (Box 118)
      - Events, 2003-2007, 1-10 of 11 folders; 919 prints (Box 119)
      - Founders' Day album, 2003, 1 photo album (Box 120)
      - Events, 2003-2007, (folder 11 of 11; 132 prints) (Box 121)
      - National Insurance Association (NIA) convention, 2003, 2 folders; 267 prints (Box 121)
      - NCCU event, 2004, 205 prints (Box 121)
      - Events, 1980-2005 and undated; 8 folders (Box 186)
      - Events, 1966-2003 and undated (Box 190-196)
        Photographs arrived in bundles and their order has been retained. Candid and posed photographs of assorted events, including employee recognition, holiday parties, meetings, annual conventions, and company trips. Also includes group and individual portraits. Some photographs contain captions, but the majority do not.
    - Historic Images, circa 1885-1952 and undated
      Contains early black-and-white images of North Carolina Mutual officers, employees, their family members, corporate meetings, office interiors, and groups related to NCM, such as Thrift Clubs, musical groups, and sports teams. These files were assembled by staff in their own separate grouping; additional historic images can also be found in the People Subseries, as well as throughout the Printed Materials Series, where they are often found reproduced in publications of many types.
      Formats are wide-ranging, and include true photographic prints, both mounted and unmounted, in albumen, platinum, and gelatin silver processes; printed images on paper; clippings; and photographic copy prints from the late 20th century. Oftentimes there are crop marks and other editorial marks made by the Publications Department staff.
      Large-format historical images of the NCM offices and its officers and employees are also found in the Oversize Prints section at the end of this series; sizes range from 11x14" to approx. 32x40"; there is also an extremely large panoramic print 27x75" of the Parrish Street home office, closed to use until conservation treatment is completed.
      Arranged alphabetically by folder title and within in loose chronological order.
      - Photographs of John M. Merrick and family, circa 1885-1915, 3 folders; 12 prints (Box 184)
        Most are mounted on ornate paper boards and appear to be a mix of albumen, platinum, and gelatin silver prints. Subjects include John Merrick; his wife Martha Hunter Merrick; daughters Martha, Alma, Mabel, and Geneva; and sons E.R. (Edward) Merrick and J.T. (John) Merrick. Photographers whose names are stamped on frames include Thomas Hobgood, Shelburn, Miss Johnson, and Cole and Holladay, all in Durham, North Carolina. An additional print of John Merrick, circa 1917, is located in the Oversize Prints subseries.
      - Portrait cabinet card of John Merrick, seated, 1890s (Box 184)
        Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
        Photographic surface is damaged; a large portion is missing.
      - Officers, circa 1890-1930s, 4 prints (Box 184)
      - Officers, reproduction of original, used for exhibit, circa 1915-1920; box size: 18x24 inches (Box OV59)
        Nine members of the original founders and officers, standing in a group facing camera. Reproduced sometime after 1970 from larger original; caption at bottom is cut off. Sheet is slightly creased due to being rolled up.
      - Studio portrait of Dr. Aaron Moore, seated, with two daughters and wife (?), circa 1900, box size: 11x14 inches (Box OV57)